# Viswanadham (Vish) Sridhara

#### CONTACT

Independent Consultant - Sivome LLC Viswanadham.Sridhara@gmail.com

Tel: (724) 590 2170

## **NETWORK**

Google Scholar | LinkedIn | Github | BitBucket | Blog

#### SUMMARY

I am a computational scientist with heavy math, modeling and simulation experience in engineering and life sciences domain. Post-PHD, I have 12+ years' experience in analyzing high-throughput –molecular data including, next-generation sequencing based genomics/transcriptomics as well as mass-spectrometry based proteomics/metabolomics data.

Recently, my focus is on using deep learning methods to analyze the high-dimensional -omics data to infer associations in the data. I usually program in Python/R using Git/Snakemake/Docker and tools specific to domain of interest.

Till date, my research work has resulted in  $\sim$ 20 peer-reviewed publications and numerous conference proceedings and poster presentations (google scholar citations:  $\sim$ 580, h-index=11).

#### **EDUCATION**

2003 - 2007, PhD, Electrical and Computer Engineering, ODU, Norfolk, VA **Dissertation:** Molecular dynamics simulations to probe effects of ultrashort high-intensity electric pulses on biological suspensions.

2001 - 2003, MS, Electrical and Computer Engineering, ODU, Norfolk, VA **Thesis:** Monte carlo analysis of millimeter-wave GaN Gunn diodes.

#### **SKILLS**

Python, R, MATLAB Git, Snakemake, Docker

#### -OMICS TOOLS

GATK, BWA, Bowtie, Samtools, BEDtools Byonic, PEAKS, Proteome Discoverer, OMSSA, MODa BioCyc, MetaCyc, GROMACS, NAMD, VMD

#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### Consultant

# **Universities, Hospitals and Startups**

Oct 2018 - Present

In my current role, I am working for a proteomics software company. In previous roles as Independent Consultant (part of 2016, 2017 and 2018) for MGH, WRI and biofuel startup

- Improved primer design for a proof-of-principle assay to capture long genomic regions.
- Built NGS pipeline and developed new computational methods for downstream analyses.
- Helped different groups with their data science and bioinformatic needs.
- Whole genome sequence (WGS) analyses, including variant analyses, copy number variation and strain specific analyses for biofuel production.
- Set-up in-house Jbrowse genome browser and Sequenceserver (blast+ web server).
- Helped analyze diverse mass-spectrometry datasets (global proteomics, phosphoproteomics) of breast cancer tissue samples.
- Integrated proteogenomics data to identify markers in laser capture microdissected breast tumor samples (Preliminary work published in AACR).

**Bioinformatics** 

# Systems Developer

#### **Booz Allen Hamilton**

March 2018 - November 2018

- Helped in automating preprocessing of gene expression data (microarray and RNA-seq) for placental datasets using raw data stored in NCBI's GEO repository (PAT Placental Atlas Tool).
- Improved analytics of differential expression, gene ontology and pathway analyses of the above preprocessed placental datasets (>20 RNA-seq and >300 microarray datasets).

#### Computational

#### Biologist

#### **UT Southwestern Medical Center**

August 2015 - April 2016

- Protein and post-translational modification identification using Proteome Discoverer, OMSSA, Sequest, MASCOT.
- Quantitative proteomics (SILAC, TMT) data analysis using MaxQuant, Proteome Discoverer.
- Bioinformatics proteomics consultant work with UT Southwestern investigators.

Research Eng/Sci

Associate V

#### The University of Texas at Austin

December 2012 - August 2015

• Built machine learning models using LASSO regression to predict bacterial growth conditions from in-silico metabolic fluxes generated from metabolic

network based flux balance analyses (FBA) methods.

- Proteomics and metabolic flux data analyses of mass-spectrometry based datasets. a. Proteomics data is analyzed using new unrestricted PTM search methods. b. Metabolic flux data is analyzed using FiatFlux software.
- Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations for Bio-electrics applications
- a. Compute intense MD simulations to understand multiple nanopore formation in lipid bilayers using advanced high performance computing environment.
- b. MD simulations to understand effects of sodium (Na) and calcium (Ca) effects in pore formation within the biological suspensions.
- Helped multiple labs with proteomics bioinformatics consulting and shortterm contracts.
- Taught computational mass-spectrometry in Big Data Summer School organized by CCBB (Center for Computational Biology and Bioinformatics every summer 4 day course)

#### Post-doc Fellow

## National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI)

June 2007 - January 2012

- Part of NCBI OMSSA (Open Mass Spectrometry Search Algorithm) project:
- a. Improved noise filtering routines/filters to accommodate high-resolution mass-spectrometry data.
- b. Optimized algorithm for ETD data analysis (ion-types, precursor peak filtering).
- c. User support by addition of requested enzymes, modifications, and other iontypes required for quantitative proteomics (iTRAQ, TMT 6-plex etc.).
- d. Improved sensitivity by adjusting for mass offsets, precursor charge assignment for low-res data. Presented related mass-spectrometry work in ASMS '08, '09, '10 and '11.
- Integration of sequence data & high-throughput phosphoproteomics data:
- a. Developed a new method (proof-of-principle) for PTM annotation on genomes (NCBI RefSeq) by using high-throughput proteomics data (PhosphoSite, PhosphoELM) and domain definitions of protein families within NCBI Conserved Domain Database (CDD).
- b. Apart from the large-scale annotation of conserved PTM sites on genomes, this method could facilitate identification of novel evolutionarily conserved posttranslational modifications.
- Developed a prototype for new class of peptide identification search algorithm OMSSA-SIM.
- a. Motivation is to remove most of the limitations faced by present generation sequence library search algorithms, for example, exact precursor mass match, unknown PTM's, mutations, different enzymatic cleavage etc. b. Preliminary work in ASMS 2011 (oral presentation in computational mass-
- b. Preliminary work in ASMS 2011 (oral presentation in computational mass-spectrometry).

#### Research Assistant

#### **Old Dominion University - Aerospace Engineering**

Summer '06 • Helped improve programming drives for a test bogie run on MAGLEV (train using magnetic levitation).

#### **Siemens Limited. Siemens Vdo Automotive**

Summer '04 • Finite element analyses (2D) to improve fuel injection solenoid models using Ansoft software.

#### **TALKS**

- Large-scale analysis of PTMs @ UT-Austin, Thermo Fisher Scientific, MD Anderson Cancer Center
- Using subspectral interval matches to make novel identifications of ETD tandem mass spectra @ ASMS 2011
- Predicting bacterial growth conditions from bacterial physiology @ Center for Systems and Synthetic Biology, UT-Austin
- Open Mass Spectrometry Search Algorithm @ George Washington University
- A comparative proteomics technique for large scale automatic annotation of posttranslational modifications on multiple genomes with reduced error rate @ NIH ProtIG Fellows seminar
- Evolutionary conservation of phosphorylation sites A mass spectrometric perspective @ NHLBI
- Time Domain Dielectric Spectroscopy Study of Jurkat Cells and Mitochondria

  @ Frank Reidy Research Center for Bioelectrics
- Time Domain Dielectric Spectroscopy Study of HL-60 cells induced by Ultra-Short pulses @ Frank Reidy Research Center for Bioelectrics

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- Tosi, L., Sridhara, V., Yang, Y., et. al., "Engineered DNA Capture Probes for Massively Multiplexed Cloning of Kilobase-Sized Genome Regions", Nature Biomedical Engineering, 2017;1. pii: 0092. doi: 10.1038/s41551-017-0092. Epub 2017 Jun 26.
- Caglar, M. U., et. al., "The E. coli molecular phenotype under different growth conditions", Scientific Reports 2017 Apr 18;7:45303. doi: 10.1038/srep45303.
- Brown, C. W., Sridhara, V., Boutz, D. R., et. al., "Large-scale analysis of post-translational modifications in E. coli under glucoselimiting conditions", BMC Genomics 2017 Apr 17;18(1):301. doi: 10.1186/s12864-017-3676-8.
- Kalantari, R., Hicks, J., Li, L., Gagnon, K., Sridhara, V., Lemoff, A., Mirzaei, H., and Corey, D. R. "Stable Association of RNAi Machinery is Conserved Between the Cytoplasm and Nucleus of Human Cells", RNA. 2016 Jul;22(7):1085-98. doi: 10.1261/rna.056499.
- Houser, J. R., et. al., Controlled measurement and comparative analysis of cellular components in E. coli reveals broad regulatory changes under long-term starvation. PLOS Computational Biology 2015 Aug 14;11(8):e1004400.
- Sridhara, V., Meyer AG, Rai P, Barrick JE, Ravikumar P, Segre D, and Wilke C.O. "Predicting growth conditions from internal metabolic fluxes in an insilico model of E. coli." (PLoS One. 2014 Dec 12;9(12):e114608.).
- Sridhara, V., Joshi, R. P. "Evaluations of a mechanistic hypothesis for the influence of extracellular ions on electroporation due to high-intensity, nanosecond pulsing." Biochimica Biophysica Acta Biomembranes, Vol.

- 1838, no. 7, Jul 2014, pp. 1793-1800.
- Sridhara, V., Joshi, R. P. "Numerical study of lipid translocation driven by nanoporation due to multiple high-intensity, ultrashort electrical pulses." Biochimica Biophysica Acta Biomembranes, Vol. 1838, no. 7, Mar 2014, pp. 902-909.
- Sridhara, V., Dina L. Bai, An Chi, Jeffrey Shabanowitz, Donald F. Hunt, Stephen H. Bryant and Lewis Y. Geer "Increasing peptide identifications and decreasing search times for ETD spectra by pre-processing and calculation of parent precursor charge." Proteome Science 2012, 10:8.
- Sridhara, V., Aron Marchler-Bauer, Stephen H. Bryant and Lewis Y. Geer, "Automatic annotation of experimentally derived, evolutionarily conserved post-translational modifications onto multiple genomes." Database (Oxford), 2011, bar019.
- Joshi, R.P., Sridhara, V., Song, J., Schoenbach, K.H "Aspects of Lipid Membrane BioResponses to Subnanosecond, Ultrahigh Voltage Pulsing." IEEE Trans. Dielectrics & Electrical Insulation, Vol. 16, no. 5, Oct 2009, pp. 1243-1250.
- Allen L. Garner, George Chen, Nianyong Chen, Viswanadham Sridhara, Juergen F. Kolb, R. James Swanson, Stephen J. Beebe, Ravindra P. Joshi, and Karl H. Schoenbach "Changes in the Dielectric Properties of Jurkat Cells Induced by Ultrashort Electrical Pulses," Biochemical Biophysical Research Communications Vol. 362, Issue. 1, Oct. 2007, pp. 139-144.
- Joshi, R.P., Nguyen, A., Sridhara, V., Nuccitelli, R., and Schoenbach, K.H., "Simulations of Calcium Release Dynamics in Response to a High-Intensity, Ultra-Short Electric Pulse," Physical review. E, Statistical, nonlinear, and soft matter physics 2007; 75(4 Pt 1):041920.
- Pliquett, U., Joshi, R.P., Sridhara, V., Schoenbach, K.H. "High Electrical Field effects on Cell Membranes." Bioelectrochemistry Vol. 70, Oct. 2006, pp. 275-282.
- Joshi, R.P., Sridhara, V., Schoenbach, K.H "Microscopic Calculations of Local Lipid Membrane Permittivities and Diffusion Coefficients for Application to Electroporation Analyses." Biochemical Biophysical Research Communications Vol. 348, Issue. 2, Sept. 2006, pp. 643648.
- Qin Hu, Sridhara, V., R. P. Joshi, J. Kolb and K.H, Schoenbach, "Molecular Dynamics Analysis of High Electric Pulse effects on Bilayer Membranes Containing DPPC and DPPS." (invited paper) IEEE Transactions on Plasma Science, Vol. 34, no. 4, Aug. 2006, pp. 1405-1411.
- Hu, Q., Sridhara, V., Joshi, R.P., Schoenbach, K.H., Beebe, S.J., Blackmore, P.F. "Simulations of transient membrane behavior in cells subjected to a high-intensity ultrashort electric pulse." Physical Review E Statistical, Nonlinear, and Soft Matter Physics, Vol. 71,no. 3, March 2005, pp. 031914(1-7).
- Joshi, R. P., Sridhara, V., Jogai, B., Shah, P., Del Rosario, R.D. "Analysis of dislocation scattering on electron mobility in GaN high electron mobility transistors." Journal of Applied Physics, Vol. 93, no. 12, Jun 15, 2003, pp. 10046-10052.
- Joshi, R. P., Sridhara, V., Shah, P., Del Rosario, R.D. "Monte Carlo analysis of GaN-based Gunn oscillators for microwave power generation." Journal of Applied Physics, Vol. 93, no. 8, Apr 15, 2003, pp. 4836-4842.

# CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

- Sridhara, V., Joshi, R.P., Hu, Q., Nguyen, A., and Schoenbach, K.H. "Simulations of cell response to high intensity, ultrashort electrical pulses" (invited paper) Bio-Electromagnetic Society Conference, Cancun, Mexico, June 11-15, 2006.
- Pliquett, U., Sridhara, V., Joshi, R.P., Swanson, R.J., and Schoenbach, K.H. "Monitoring intrastructural changes in Jurkat cells after nanosecond pulsed electric field application." Electromed 2005 Conference, Portland, OR, May 15-18, 2005.
- Garner, A.L., Chen, G., Chen, N., Sridhara, V., Kolb, J. F., Swanson, R.J., Beebe, S.J., Joshi, R.P., and Schoenbach, K.H. "Changes in the Dielectric Properties of Jurkat and HL-60 cells after Electrical Pulses." Electromed 2005 Conference, Portland, OR, May 15-18, 2005.

#### **POSTERS**

- Sridhara, V et. al., "Integrated proteogenomic analysis of laser capture microdissected breast tumors", AACR 2017.
- Tchafa, A et. al., "High resolution diagnostic platform for breast cancer therapy management", Proceedings of the AACR 2016.
- Sridhara V et. al., "Large-scale analysis of post-translational modifications in E. coli grown under glucose limiting conditions" EMBL Conference, Heidelberg, Germany, Nov 8-11, 2014.
- Houser JR, et. al., "Controlled Measurements of Multiple Cellular Components in E. coli As a Resource for Integrative Computational Modeling of Cellular Subsystems", Synthetic Biology: Engineering, Evolution and Design (SEED).
- Sridhara V et. al., "Analysis of metabolic fluxes in E. coli over time", AG3C annual meeting, May 2014.
- Sridhara V et. al., "Predicting bacterial growth conditions from bacterial physiology", 1st Annual symposium in Big Data in Biology, The University of Texas at Austin, May 2013.
- Sridhara V et. al., "A Comparative Proteomics Technique for the Automatic Annotation of PostTranslational Modifications on Multiple Genomes at Reduced Error Rate." ASMS 2010
- Sridhara V et. al., "Decreasing Database Search Times in ETD MS/MS Sequence Searching by Assignment of Parent Precursor Charge to MS/MS Spectra." ASMS 2009
- Sridhara V et. al., Lewis Y. Geer and Stephen H. Bryant "Increasing True Positive Rates in MS/MS Sequence Searching Algorithms by Incorporating Corrections to Precursor Mass Calculations." ASMS 2008
- Sridhara, V., et al., "Molecular Dynamics Simulations to Probe Electric-Pulse Induced Micelle Formation and Ion-Channel Regulation in Biological Cells", ODU RD 2006 (Honorable mention)
- Hu, Q., et al., "Dynamical modeling studies of model membranes and cellular response to nanosecond ultrashort pulses", ODU RD 2005(Poster awarded 3rd place)